<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>wp-SwimTeam - a Wordpress Plugin for Swim Team Managment</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Mike</firstname>

      <surname>Walsh</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>www.wp-swimteam.org</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>4/29/2010</pubdate>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Background</title>

    <section>
      <title>MacGregor Downs MacDolphins Swim Team</title>

      <para>I have three children who swim for the MacDolphins and my wife has
      been an active volunteer for many years. At the end of the 2007 summer
      season my wife was approached to chair the swim team for the 2008
      season. </para>

      <para>She agreed, not knowing what she was getting into!Like many summer
      swim teams, the MacDolphins were run by an ad-hoc group of volunteers.
      The leadership positions turned over frequently and just about
      everything was done by hand. Registration, volunteers, rosters, heat
      sheets - just everything the swim team did was on paper or existed on
      someone's computer in Word or Excel. Each season the person in charge
      litterally had to start all over.</para>

      <para>My wife knew this going when she took on the position but didn't
      know how bad it was. When she took the job she asked me if I would help
      her computerize the MacDolphins. I said "sure, how hard can it be?".
      Little did I know ....</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Computerizing the MacDolphins</title>

      <para>In late 2007 I began the process of computerizing the MacDolphins.
      I was presented with some basic requirements so I had a rough idea of
      what team wanted and needed. The early requirements consisted of
      these:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Computerized Registration</para>

          <para>No more paper forms with hard to read handwriting. We had
          swimmers with wrong birthdays, misspelled names, all sorts of data
          entry errors simply because people didn't write legibly.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Web Presence</para>

          <para>The MacDolphins wanted a web site. While the MacDolphins are
          part of <link linkend="???">MacGregor Downs Country Club</link>, the
          club's web site didn't feature the swim team prominently and getting
          information posted on it was a tedious process.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>E-Mail Distribution List</para>

          <para>The swim team did not have a mechanism to communicate quickly
          or effectively to parents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Swim Times</para>

          <para>Because of the ad-hoc nature the team was being run, there
          were no records of swim times. Parents and swimmers wanted their
          times and the coaches were seeding the meets based on gut feel and
          not real data. Times had been kept in Excel in past years but
          somewhere they got lost and there was no ownership of the
          problem.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>With these basic requirements I set off in search of solutions.
      Before I got involved, the swim team had started looking at Hy-tek Team
      Manager since that is what was used for our local CIty Invitational
      Meet. I did some reading on Team Manager, concluded it would do what we
      needed from a time and seeding perspective, and began looking at the
      other requirements.</para>

      <para>Like many swim teams, we didn't have a large budget to work with
      so I was looking for free or low cost solutions. There are a host of
      free web offerings which all could help but I didn't find anything that
      really solved what we wanted solved. Doodle and MySignUp.com offered
      solutions for volunteer sign up. Yahoo Groups and Google Groups offered
      e-mail distribution. There are a host of free web site offerings and
      blog services. All of the sports team web site solutions I found were
      focused on stick and ball sports and not well suited to swim team. The
      only thing that I found which looked like a fit was Hy-tek's Active
      Network but the cost was more than we were willing to take on.</para>

      <para>We didn't want the MacDolphins scattered across half a dozen web
      sites each requring different registration and login requirements I
      started to think that building our own web site was the best solution. I
      had used Wordpress for several other small projects so I was familiar
      with it and knew that it could do a lot of what we wanted and the plugin
      system would probably be sufficient to build what I couldn't
      find.</para>

      <para>Very quickly I had a domain registered and a web site set up to
      show the leadership committee what could be done. The idea of everything
      being in one central location was very appealing so with the leardership
      committee's blessing, I started to build what has become the wp-SwimTeam
      Wordpress plugin.</para>

      <para>There wasn't a lot of time between when I started and swim team
      registration so I focused on getting the data model correct to support
      the registration process.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
